Lee De Forest
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
Papers of Lee De Forest 1884-1955
MSS18168
De Forest, Lee, 1873-1961
375 items 4 containers 1.6 linear feet 2 microfilm reels
Manuscript Division Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Radio pioneer and inventor. Correspondence, diaries, technical notes and other material relating to Lee De Forest's inventions in radio and electronics and their effect in sound recording and transmission, efforts to exploit his discoveries through various business ventures, and his competition with Guglielmo Marconi in the field of wireless communication.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the Library's online catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically therein.
Names:
De Forest, Lee, 1873-1961; Marconi, Guglielmo, marchese, 1874-1937; Yale University--Students
Subjects:
Electronics; Inventions; Preparatory schools; Radio; Sound--Recording and reproducing; Sound--Transmission; Wireless communication systems
Occupations:
Inventors; Radio pioneers
Administrative Information
Provenance:
The papers of Lee De Forest, radio pioneer and inventor, were given to the Library of Congress by De Forest in 1955.
Microfilm:
A microfilm edition of part of these papers is available on two reels. Consult a reference librarian in the Manuscript Division concerning availability for purchase or interlibrary loan.
Biographical Note
Date Event
1873, Aug. 26 Born, Council Bluffs, Iowa
1896 Ph.B., Yale University, New Haven, Conn.
1899 Ph.D., Yale University, New Haven, Conn.
1900 Joined Western Electric Co., Chicago, Ill. Designed alternating current transmitter Developed electrolytic receiver
1901 Founded American De Forest Wireless Telegraph Co. (later United Wireless Telegraph Co.)
1905 Developed first model of audion amplifier
1906 Developed triode vacuum tube Married Lucille Sheardown (divorced 1907)
1908 Married Nora Blatch (divorced 1911)
1910 Broadcast voice of Enrico Caruso by radio from the Metropolitan Opera House, New York, N.Y.
1912 Sold telephone repeater rights to American Telephone and Telegraph Co., which used his three electrode vacuum tube in first transcontinental telephony Married Mary Mayo (divorced 1930)
1913 Demonstrated first oscillating audion tube Became vice president, Radio Telegraph Co. Became vice president, De Forest Radio Co.
1916 Made first radio news broadcast Established radio broadcast station
1919 Patented phonofilm device for making talking pictures
ca. 1920 Published
How to Set Up an Amateur Radio Receiving Station (New York, N.Y.: De Forest Radio Telephone and Telegraph Co. 32 pp.)
ca. 1922 Published
Wireless in the Home (New York, N.Y.: De Forest Radio Telephone and Telegraph Co. 32 pp.)
1923 Demonstrated sound on film at Rivoli Theater, New York, N.Y. Organized De Forest Phonofilm Co.
1926 D.Sc., Yale University, New Haven, Conn.
1930 Married Marie Mosquini
1934 Established Lee De Forest, Inc., Los Angeles, Calif.
1942 Published
Television, Today and Tomorrow (New York, N.Y.: Dial Press. 361 pp.)
1947 Edison Medal of the American Institute of Electrical Engineers
1950 Published
Father of Radio (Chicago, Ill.: Wilcox and Fallett. 502 pp.)
1951 Vice president, National Association for Better Radio and Television
1961, June 30 Died, Hollywood, Calif.
Scope and Content Note
The papers of Lee De Forest (1873-1961) span the years 1884-1955 and include biographical sketches, booklets, correspondence, diaries, drawings, essays, newspaper and magazine clippings, photographs, poetry, and research notes. De Forest was a pioneer in wireless communications who made possible the long distance transmission and reception of the human voice, which led to the foundation of the radio industry and long distance telephone communication. His inventions, particularly the audion amplifier in 1905, the triode vacuum tube in 1906, and the oscillating audion in 1913, revolutionized wireless communications and earned him the title, “the father of radio.” De Forest also perfected the phonofilm method of sound recording and the glow-light recording of sound films, made important contributions to the development of television and high speed facsimile transmission, and invented radio therapy and the radio knife.
The collection contains letters from De Forest to members of his family, friends, and business associates, with only a few to fellow scientists. The correspondence is arranged chronologically. A subject file contains biographical material on De Forest, published and manuscript scientific writings, photographs of early audion tubes, and technical schematics, sketches, and notes on several of De Forest's inventions. The subject file is arranged alphabetically by type of material.
De Forest's diaries, or notebook journals, span the years 1891-1949 and contain references to the difficulties encountered in the early years of his career as he struggled for recognition in the face of persistent lack of funds and inconstant friends. There are frequent allusions to his inventions and business ventures, both successes and failures, descriptions of the natural world, and original poetry. The diaries are arranged chronologically and have been microfilmed.
Container List
- Correspondence, 1884-1950, n.d., (29 folders) (Box 1)
- Subject file (Box 2)
  - Clippings, 1890-1953, n.d., (2 folders)
  - La Lumière Électrique, 1911
  - Photographs
    - Early audions, n.d.
    - Personal, n.d.
  - Printed matter, 1904-1950, n.d.
  - Schematics, sketches, and technical notes, 1910-1911, n.d., (2 folders)
  - Yale University, New Haven, Conn., entrance examination, biographical sketch, and class book form, 1892-1937, n.d.
  - Writings, 1896-1955, n.d.
- Diaries
  Microfilm edition available. Shelf no. 17,174
  - Vols. 1-15, 1891-1902 (Box 3, Reel 1)
  - Vols. 16-23, 1903-1949 (Box 4, Reel 2)